Guide to the Sergei Evreinow Correspondence and Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Sergeĭ Aleksandrovich Evreinow correspondence and papers
1926-1959
GEN MSS 296
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.6
(2 boxes)
52 ALS and 15 TLS from N. N. Evreinov to Sergeĭ Aleksandrovich Evreinow, 6 carbons of letters from Sergeĭ Aleksandrovich Evreinow to N. N. Evreinov. Also includes correspondence between Sergeĭ Aleksandrovich Evreinow and Anna Aleksandrovna Evreinova, Arthur Lourié, and various printed materials (theatrical programs, clippings, memorial notices) and photographs relating to N. N. Evreinov.
Evreinow, Sergeĭ Aleksandrovich, ca. 1895-1953
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Francis R. T. Evreinov, 1968.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 2: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
SERGEI ALEKSANDROVICH EVREINOW (ca. 1895-1953)
Sergei Aleksandrovich Evreinow, born in Russia ca. 1895, was an accomplished musician who ran a music distribution business. His own interests are reflected in his correspondence with Ivan Lapshin, Artur Lur'e (Arthur Lourie), and Vladimir Nikolaevich Skriabin, a descendant of the composer. Little further information is available about S. A. Evreinow; the correspondence indicates that he had probably arrived in America at a young age, since he could read N. N. Evreinov's letters in Russian but preferred to reply in French.
Sergei Aleksandrovich was a distant relative of the renowned Russian dramatist, theater director and historian Nikolai Nikolaevich Evreinov. N. N. Evreinov was born February 13/25 1879. He studied music composition under Nikolay Rimsky-Korsakov and Alexander Glazunov, as a photograph of the three, located among the papers, testifies. In 1907-1908, and again in 1911-1912, N. N. Evreinov directed seasons of antique plays at "Starinnyi teatr"; in 1908 he directed Gabriele d'Annunzio's Francesca di Rimini at V. F. Kommisarzhevskaia's theater, and from 1910 to 1916 he collaborated in the theater "Krivoe zerkalo". These productions not only made him known as a daring and brilliant director and playwright, but also gave him much material for his historical studies of the stage. His ideas of the "theatricalization of life" and the "monodrama" remain influential in modern drama, and some of his plays have been found to presage Expressionism and the theater of the absurd.
After some equivocation, in 1925 Evreinov decided to remain permanently outside Russia. His European renown allowed him to continue his tireless theatrical and publishing activities from Paris. During the 1930s, he worked on several motion pictures in France. In 1935, Evreinov was honored with an invitation to direct at the Paris National Theater. As his letters to S. A. Evreinow show, Evreinov and his wife, Anna Aleksandrovna Kashina-Evreinova, weathered the German occupation and post-war depression quite badly. Still, he continued to write and publish quite prolifically until his death on September 7, 1953.
Scope and Contents
Series I, Correspondence, largely consists of N. N. Evreinov's letters to S. A. Evreinow. These provide a fascinating portrait of the dramatist's strong personality and a record of his artistic triumphs and financial difficulties. The two men apparently met in 1926 in New York, where Evreinov was attempting to enter into the American theater world and arrange translations of his "countless" books. Apart from a series of lectures in various cities, one concrete result was Evreinov's 1927 book The Theatre in Life. Some of the correspondence refers to productions of Evreinov's plays, particularly to that of Korabl' pravednykh at New York's Irving Place Art Theatre in 1926, and of The Chief Thing at Harvard in 1926 [?] and at Tufts College in 1949 (on this latter production see also Evreinow's correspondence with Marston Balch). A significant portion of the correspondence reflects a shared interest in clarifying the nature of their kinship; in later years, S. A. Evreinow even undertook a special genealogical study, the results of which he communicated to N. N. Evreinov. The correspondence between Evreinov and Evreinow shows that Sergei Aleksandrovich supported his distant relative quite generously in times of need, both in 1927, when Evreinov encountered some difficulties in New York, and in the post-war years. He became a close friend of the family, traveling to Paris to visit the Evreinovs. After Evreinov's death, Sergei Aleksandrovich continued to correspond with his widow. S. A. Evreinow's correspondence with Ivan Lapshin, Arthur Lourie and Vladimir Nikolaevich Skriabin testifies to his own interests in music, especially the works of Scriabin.
Series II, Other Papers, includes notices and programs of N. N. Evreinov's works in the United States, including the 1927 production of The Chief Thing. Here one also finds obituary and commemorative items, as well as two photographs of the dramatist, one with his family and one with his teachers Rimsky-Korsakov and Glazunov. The series also encompasses some items bearing on S. A. Evreinow's own interests, such as clippings from the Russian-language press and materials concerning the demise of one Jacob Weinberg.
Russian drama -- 20th Century; Theater -- Russia -- 20th Century; Theatrical producers and directors -- Russia; Photographic prints; Evreinov, N. N. (Nikolaĭ Nikolaevich), 1879-1953; Evreinow, Sergeĭ Aleksandrovich, ca. 1895-1953; Kashina-Evreinova, Anna Aleksandrovna; Lourié, Arthur, 1892-1966; Scriabin, Aleksandr Nikolayevich, 1872-1915; Weinberg, Jacob, 1879-1956
- Correspondence, Series I
  - LETTERS FROM NIKOLAI NIKOLAEVICH EVREINOV
    - Letters, 1926-49 (Box 1, Folder 1-10)
    - Letters, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Scope and Contents
      Envelope date 1950 Jun 20 includes part of carbon of S. A. Evreinow's reply on verso
    - Letters, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Letter of 1951 Jun 17 includes part of carbon of S. A. Evreinow's reply on verso
    - Letters, 1952-53 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - LETTERS FROM ANNA ALEKSANDROVNA KASHINA-EVREINOVA
    - Letters, 1949-56, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - LETTERS FROM OTHERS
    - Balch, Marston, 1950 Nov 30 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Lapshin, Ivan, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lourie, Arthur, 1953 Apr 1 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Also spelled Artur Lur'e
    - Skriabin, Vladimir Nikolaevich, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Yarmolinsky, Avraham, 1948 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Unidentified, 1946-49, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - LETTERS TO NIKOLAI NIKOLAEVICH EVREINOV
    - Letters, 1948-53, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22-24)
  - LETTERS TO ANNA ALEKSANDROVNA KASHINA-EVREINOVA
    - Letter, 1954 Jan 19 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - LETTERS TO OTHERS
    - Balch, Marston, 1949-50 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Unidentifed, 1959, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Other Papers, Series II
  - MATERIALS CONCERNING N. N. EVREINOV
    - Poster for Lecture, 1926 Oct 17 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "Prologue: The Tufts College Theater": incl. program of "The Chief Thing", 1949 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Clippings on decease, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Funeral and commemorative notices, 1953-54 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Clippings, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Photograph with Nikolay Rimsky- Korsakov and A. K. Glazunov (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Photograph with A. A. Kashina- Evreinova, Iraida Kashina, and N. I. Butkovskaia (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - MISC
    - Tickets to charity concert, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Clippings by L. L. Sabaneev, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "Delo Kornilova": clipping, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence and clippings re Jacob Weinberg, 1956-57 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Clipping and business card (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 1 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Box 1, folder 2 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Box 1, folder 7 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Box 1, folder 8 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Box 1, folder 9 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Box 1, folder 10 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Box 1, folder 11 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Box 1, folder 12 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Box 1, folder 13 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Box 1, folder 14 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Box 1, folder 31 (Box 2, Folder 50)